<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Waste Land SDE</title>
                <author>T. S. Eliot</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Edited by</resp>
                    <name>Sebastiano Giacomini</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>First edition, <date>1922</date>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt><publisher>University of Bologna</publisher>
                <availability status="unknown">
                    <p>This work is the property of the University of Bologna. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <settlement>New York</settlement>
                    <repository>Public Library</repository>
                    <idno type="Bod">Cup.410.g.63</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <title>The Waste Land</title>
                            <author>T. S. Eliot</author>
                            <date>1922</date>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <titlePage>
                <pb xml:id="wasteland-i" n="i"/>
                <div xml:id="page-i" >
                    <p>
                        <figure><graphic url="https://thewwwasteland.github.io/images/1.jpg" xml:id="page-1"/>
                        </figure>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <head>
                            <line>THE WASTE LAND<lb/></line>
                            <line>By<lb/></line>
                            <line>T. S. Eliot<lb/></line>
                        </head>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <quote>
                    
                            <line>"Did he live his life again in every detail of desire, tempta-<lb/></line>
                            <line>tion, and surrender during that supreme moment of complete<lb/></line>
                            <line>knowledge? He cried in a whisper at some image, at some vi-<lb/></line>
                            <line>sion, - he cried out twice, a cry that was no more than a<lb/></line>
                            <line>breath -<lb/></line>
                            <line>        'The horror!   The horror!'"<lb/></line>
                        </quote>
                        <ref>    
                            <line>                                      <app><rdg>Conrad.</rdg></app></line>
                        </ref>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </titlePage>
        </front>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="wasteland-1" n="1"/>
            <div xml:id="page-2">
                <p>
                    <figure><graphic url="https://thewwwasteland.github.io/images/2.jpg" xml:id="page-1"/>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <head>
                        <line>HE DO THE POLICE IN DIFFERENT VOICES: Part I.<lb/></line>
                        <line><lb/></line>
                        <line>THE BURIAL OF THE DEAD<lb/></line>
                    </head>
                </p>
                <p><app><del xml:id="rdg-2">
                    <l>First we had a couple of feelers down at Tom's place</l>
                    <l>There was old Tom, boiled to eyes, blind,</l>
                    <l>(Don't you remember that time after a dance,</l>
                    <l>Top hats and all, we and Silk Hat Harry,</l>
                    <l>And old Tom took us behind, brought out a bottle of fizz,</l>
                    <l>With old Jane, Tom's Wife; and we got Joe to sing</l>
                    <lg xml:id="rdg-3">
                        <l>"I'm proud of all the Irish blood that's in me,</l>
                        <l>"There's not a man can say a word agin me").</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lb/><l>Then we had dinner in good form, and a couple of Bengal lights.</l>
                    <l>When we got into the show, up in Row A,</l>
                    <l>I tried to put my food in the drum, and didn't the girl squeal,</l>
                    <l>She never did take to me, a nice guy-but rough;</l>
                    <l>The next thing we were out in the street, Oh was it cold!</l>
                    <l>When will you be good? Blew in to the Opera Exchange,</l>
                    <l>Sopped up some gin, sat in to the cork game,</l>
                    <l>Mr. Fay was there, singing "The Maid of The Mill";</l>
                    <l>Then we thought we'd breeze along and take a walk.</l>
                    <l>Then we lost Steve.</l>
                    <l>("I turned up an hour later down at Myrtle's place.</l>
                    <l>What d'y' mean, she says, at two o'clock in the morning,</l>
                    <l>I'm not busy here for guys like you;</l>
                    <l>We've only had a raid last week, I've been warned twice.</l>
                    <l><rdg xml:id="rdg-4"><del xml:id="del-4">Sergeant, I said</del></rdg>, I've kept a decent house for twenty years,</l>
                    <l>There's three gents from the Buckingham Club upstairs now,</l>
                    <l>I'm going to retire and live on a farm, she says,</l>
                    <l>There's no money in it now, what with the damage done,</l>
                    <l>And the reputation the place gets, <lem><del xml:id="del-5">on account</del></lem><rdg xml:id="rdg-5">off</rdg> of a few bar-flies,</l>
                    <l>I've kept a clean house for twenty years, she says,</l>
                    <l>And the gents from Buckingham Club know they're safe here;</l>
                    <l>You was well introduced, but this is the last of you.</l>
                    <l>Get me a woman, I said; you're too drunk, she said,</l>
                    <l>But she gave me a bed, and a bath, and ham and eggs,</l>
                    <l>And now you go get a shave, she said; <rdg xml:id="rdg-6"><del xml:id="del-6">I had a good laugh,</del></rdg></l>
                    <l>Myrtle <rdg xml:id="rdg-7"><del xml:id="del-7">was</del></rdg> always a <rdg xml:id="rdg-8"><del xml:id="del-8">good sport").</del></rdg> treated me white.</l>
                    <l>We'd just gone up the alley, a fly cop came along,</l>
                    <l>Looking for trouble; committing a nuisance, he said,</l> 
                    <l>You come on to the station. I'm sorry, I said,</l>
                    <l>It's no use being sorry, he said; let me get my hat, I said.</l>                    
                    <l>Well by a stroke of luck who came by but Mr.Donovan.</l>                    
                    <l>What's this, officer. You're new on this beat, aint you?</l>                    
                    <l><rdg xml:id="rdg-9.1"><del xml:id="del-9.1">I thought so. You know who I am? Yes, I do,</del></rdg></l>                   
                    <l><rdg xml:id="rdg-9.2"><del xml:id="del-9.2">Said the fresh cop, very peevish.</del></rdg> Then let it alone,</l>                   
                    <l>These gents are particular friends of mine.</l>                    
                    <l>-Wasn't it luck? Then we wen to the German Club,</l>                    
                    <l>We and Mr. Donovan and his friend <rdg xml:id="rdg-10"><del xml:id="del-10">Joe Leahy</del></rdg></l>                    
                                                          
                </del></app></p>
                <note id="note-1"><del><lg>
                        <l>Meet me in the shadow of the</l>
                        <l>watermelon Vine</l>
                        <l>Eva Iva Uva Emmaline</l>
                    </lg></del>
                </note>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
